Guide to the Martin Allen Pond Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Martin Allen Pond papers
1935-1982
MS 1376
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
11
The papers consist of correspondence, reports, typescripts, manuscripts, and printed material of M. Allen Pond, documenting his professional work in the field of public health.
Pond, M. Allen, 1912-1995
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Medical Historical Library, 1983. Gift of M. Allen Pond, 1988 and 1990, and of Mrs. M. Allen Pond, 1998.
Arrangement
Arranged in two series and three additions: I. General Correspondence, 1948-1970. II. Topical Files, 1935-1976.
Scope and Contents
The M. Allen Pond Papers contain correspondence, reports, printed material, typescripts, and manuscripts chiefly relating to Pond's career with the U.S. Public Health Service (1942-1946, 1948-1968). The papers were transferred to Sterling Library from the Historical Medical Library in 1983. The eight linear feet of papers are arranged in two series and three additions.
Series I: The bulk of the chronologically arranged General Correspondence dates from 1960-1968 and consists of letters and memoranda between Pond and legislators, government agency officials, Public Health Service staff members, and individuals concerning agency policies and public health legislation. A few letters of a personal nature are interfiled within the series.
Series II: Correspondence, articles, reports, policy statements, congressional publications, presidential messages, and speeches contained in alphabetically arranged topical files form three-quarters of the second series. These materials reflect the prominent public health issues of the 1950s and 60s in the United States, specifically reinsurance, health insurance, health care for the aged, health professions educational assistance, the Salk vaccine, and urban health. Articles and reports on housing codes, ordinances, and other topics from state and federal housing agencies and professional associations (1935-1965) relate to Pond's work in housing health and sanitation and form the remainder of the second series.
Typescripts and reprints of papers and articles which Pond presented at conferences and seminars and which were subsequently published in professional journals are contained in files bearing the conference or seminar name. An additional file, "Housing - Speeches, Articles and Reports," contains nine papers by Pond as well as a list of speeches and reports on housing written by Pond from 1943-1949.
Biographical / Historical
Martin Allen Pond (1912-) graduated from Yale University (B.S. in Engineering, 1935; M.P.H., 1936) and was instructor in Public Health (1936-1941), assistant professor (1941-1942, 1946-1948), lecturer (1948), and sanitary inspector for the Department of University Health (1946-1948). He served in the U.S. Public Health Service as director of the health and sanitation program in war housing built by the Federal Public Housing Authority (1942-1946); assistant chief sanitary engineering officer; chief, Division of Engineering Resources; coordinator of the Community Facilities Program; staff assistant, Office of the Secretary, U.S. Department of Health, Education and Welfare (1948-1953); and Assistant Surgeon General (1963-1968). In 1968 Pond joined the public health faculty of the University of Pittsburg where he became associate dean (1969-1974), acting dean (1980-1981), and dean emeritus (1981-present) of the Graduate School of Public Health.
General
This collection forms part of the Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Housing and health; Health insurance; Public health; Sanitary engineering; Educators; Health-officers; Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection; Pond, M. Allen, 1912-1995; United States. Public Health Service; University of Pittsburg -- Faculty; Yale University -- Faculty
- Correspondence, 1948-1970; Series I; 3 linear feet (7 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains material arranged in chronological order.
  - General
    - 1948-1960 July (Box 1, Folder 1-25)
    - 1960 August - 1962 May 1960 August - 1962 May (Box 2, Folder 26-48)
    - 1962 June - 1964 February 1962 June - 1964 February (Box 3, Folder 49-72)
    - 1964 March - 1965 September (Box 4, Folder 73-95)
    - 1965 October - 1966 September (Box 5, Folder 96-110)
    - 1966 October - 1967 August (Box 6, Folder 111-123)
    - 1967 September - 1968 September, undated (Box 7, Folder 124-137)
- Topical Files, 1935-1976; Series II; 5 linear feet (12 boxes)
  This series contains materials arranged alphabetically by topic.
  - Advisory councils, 1957-1959 (Box 8, Folder 159)
  - Aid to medical education, 1955-1975 (Box 8, Folder 160-161)
  - Aid to schools of public health, 1955-1959 (Box 8, Folder 162)
  - Bayne-Jones committee, 1957-1959, undated (Box 8, Folder 163-165)
  - Children's Bureau, 1956-1957 (Box 8, Folder 166)
  - Department of Health, Education and Welfare, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 167)
  - Federal employee health insurance, 1955-1959 (Box 8, Folder 168)
  - General insurance, 1954 (Box 8, Folder 169)
  - Health care of aged, 1960 (Box 8, Folder 170)
  - Health insurance
    - General
      - 1952-1954 (Box 8, Folder 171-173)
      - 1955-1959 (Box 9, Folder 174-184)
    - Aged, 1957-1960 (Box 9, Folder 185-186)
    - Legislation
      - Administration Pooling bill, 1956 (Box 9, Folder 187)
      - Administration Reinsurance bill, 1955 (Box 9, Folder 188)
      - Major proposals, 1958 (Box 10, Folder 189)
      - 83rd Congress, 1954, undated (Box 10, Folder 190-191)
      - 83rd and prior congresses, 1954, undated (Box 10, Folder 192)
      - 84th Congress, 1955-1957, undated (Box 10, Folder 193)
      - 85th Congress, 1957-1958, undated (Box 10, Folder 194)
      - 86th Congress
        - General, 1959-1960 (Box 10, Folder 195)
        - Administration proposal, 1960 (Box 10, Folder 196)
    - Medical Economics of Aged Task Force, 1957-1960 (Box 10, Folder 197-198)
    - Pond, M. Allen, 1956-1964, undated (Box 10, Folder 199-200)
    - Social Security approach, 1957-1960 (Box 11, Folder 201)
    - Tax exemptions, 1953-1954 (Box 11, Folder 202)
    - Unemployed coverage, 1950-1958, undated (Box 11, Folder 203-206)
  - Health manpower in selected occupations, 1963 (Box 11, Folder 207)
  - Health meeting briefing materials, 1962 (Box 11, Folder 208-211)
  - Health messages, 1955-1958 (Box 11, Folder 212)
  - Health needs and goods, 1964-1965 (Box 11, Folder 213)
  - "Health of the Nation": president's message, 1964 (Box 11, Folder 214-215)
  - Health Professions Educational Assistance Act
    - General, 1963 (Box 12, Folder 216-217)
    - House of Representatives, 1963 (Box 12, Folder 218-219)
  - Hill-Burton meeting, 1957-1958 (Box 12, Folder 220)
  - Hoover Commission, 1955-1957 (Box 12, Folder 221)
  - House hearings
    - General, 1955 (Box 12, Folder 222-223)
    - Omnibus bill, 1955 (Box 12, Folder 224)
  - Housing
    - Agencies, 1946-1947, undated (Box 12, Folder 225)
    - American Institute of Architects, 1965 (Box 12, Folder 226)
    - Architecture conferences, 1956-1959 (Box 12, Folder 227-228)
    - Book, 1947-1949, undated (Box 13, Folder 229)
    - Codes, 1942-1951, undated (Box 13, Folder 230)
    - Committee on Hygiene of Housing
      - General, 1940-1947, undated (Box 13, Folder 231-233)
      - Reports, 1936-1937, undated (Box 13, Folder 234)
    - Courses, 1947, undated (Box 13, Folder 235)
    - "Development of a Local Health Department Housing Program,", 1952-1953, undated (Box 13, Folder 236)
    - Health Department in housing, 1945-1947, undated (Box 13, Folder 237)
    - Health relationship, 1940-1950, undated (Box 13, Folder 238-239)
    - Illumination, 1945, undated (Box 13, Folder 240)
    - League of Nations reports, 1935-1938, undated (Box 13, Folder 241)
    - Lighting for low cost housing, 1938, 1947 (Box 13, Folder 242)
    - Lighting survey, 1939-1947, undated (Box 14, Folder 243)
    - Mental health, 1945-1950, undated (Box 14, Folder 244)
    - Michigan seminar, 1946 (Box 14, Folder 245)
    - Minnesota seminar, 1946, undated (Box 14, Folder 246)
    - National Association of Housing and Redevelopment Officials, 1946 (Box 14, Folder 247)
    - Principles of Healthful Housing, 1935, 1938 (Box 14, Folder 248)
    - Research survey, 1947-1950, undated (Box 14, Folder 249)
    - Speeches, articles and reports, 1950, undated (Box 14, Folder 250)
    - Subcommittee on Environmental Standards, 1945-1948 (Box 14, Folder 251)
    - Subcommittee on Housing Regulations, 1947, 1959 (Box 14, Folder 252)
    - Subcommittee on Research, 1942, 1943, 1947 (Box 14, Folder 253)
    - Subcommittee on Standards for Construction, 1946-1948, undated (Box 14, Folder 254)
    - Subcommittee on Standards for Installed Household Equipment, 1944-1945, undated (Box 14, Folder 255)
  - Legislative proposals
    - General, 1964 (Box 14, Folder 256-262, Box 15)
    - Specifications, 1967 (Box 15, Folder 263-264)
    - United States Public Health Service, 1964 (Box 15, Folder 265-267)
  - Medical care in modern society, undated (Box 15, Folder 268)
  - Medical school construction, 1963 (Box 15, Folder 269-270)
  - Mental health, 1962-1963 (Box 15, Folder 271-272)
  - Mental illness, 1955-1959 (Box 15, Folder 273)
  - National Conference on Social Welfare, 1961-1965, undated (Box 15, Folder 274-275)
  - Nurse Training Act, 1964 (Box 15, Folder 276-278, Box 16)
  - Occupational health, 1953, 1971 (Box 15, Folder 279, Box 16)
  - Poliomyelitis vaccination program references, 1956 (Box 15, Folder 280-282, Box 16)
  - Progressive patient care, 1956 (Box 16, Box 15, Folder 283)
  - Public Health Service
    - Accident prevention, 1964 (Box 16, Box 15, Folder 284)
    - Legislative proposals, 1968 (Box 16, Box 15, Folder 285-286)
    - Materials, 1962, 1967 (Box 16, Box 15, Folder 287-288)
  - Public health training, 1963-1964 (Box 15, Folder 289-291, Box 16)
  - Radiological health
    - 1956-1957 (Box 15, Folder 292, Box 16)
    - 1958-1959 (Box 17, Folder 293-294)
  - Reinsurance, 1954-1955 (Box 17, Folder 295-298)
  - Reinsurance Fact Book, 1954-1955 (Box 17, Folder 299-301)
  - Reorganization of the Bureau of State Services, 1954 (Box 17, Folder 302-305)
  - Roberts' Subcommittee hearings, 1963 (Box 17, Folder 306-307)
  - Salk vaccine, 1955-1976 (Box 18, Folder 308-309)
  - Senate Committee Hearings on air pollution, 1966 (Box 18, Folder 310-313)
  - Southern Methodist University seminar, 1964-1965 (Box 18, Folder 313)
  - Task forces
    - Accident prevention, 1966 (Box 18, Folder 314-315)
    - Injury control, 1964 (Box 18, Folder 316)
  - Urban health
    - General, 1964-1968 (Box 18, Folder 317-319)
    - Surgeon General's Advisory Committee, 1963-1965 (Box 19, Folder 320)
  - Urban water supply and sewage systems, 1964 (Box 19, Folder 321-323)
  - United States Public Health Service legislation, 1967 (Box 19, Folder 324-326)
  - Water pollution control, 1955-1959 (Box 19, Folder 327)
- Additional Material, 1954-1970; Accession 1989-M-028; 1.75 linear feet (4 boxes)
  Addition Inventory by Carol King, 1988 November
  Received from: M. Allen Pond
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - Folsom, Marion B., 1955 December - 1964 December, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    - Keefer, Chester S., 1955 September - 1964 April (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - McGuinness, Aims C., 1957 August - 1964 February (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Perkins, Rosewell B., 1956 November - 1964 March (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - TOPICAL FILES
    - Air pollution, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Conference on Preventive Medicine and Social Science Research, 1958 June 22-27 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Conference on Urban Planning for Environmental Health, "Progressive Health Services,", 1962 April 24 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Connecticut Public Health Association, "Planning for Health: A New National Purpose,", 1967 April 11 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Department of Health, Education and Welfare, Public Health Service, Division of Air Pollution, 1963, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Eleventh National Meeting of the Public Health Conference on Records and Statistics, Washington, D.C., "Manpower, Facilities, and Planning for Tomorrow's Health Programs,", 1966 June 20-24 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Environmental Health, 1963-1968 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Health services gap areas, 1955, 1960, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - International Insurance Conference, "Public Health Trends and Problems,", 1957 May 22 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - National Conference of Health and Welfare Plans Trustees and Administrators, "Medical and Hospital Costs,", 1958 September 10 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Occupational Health, "Frye Report,", 1965-1968, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Pesticides, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Politics of Social Change: Abortion Reform--A Case Study, 1970 October 26 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Preliminary Review and Recommendations Concerning Public Health Service Facilities Construction, Equipment, and Related Environmental "Standards,", 1967 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - President's Commission on Heart Disease, Cancer, and Stroke, 1963-1964 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - President's Messages, 1954-1965 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - "Proposal for an Environmental Health Center for the U.S. Public Health Service,", 1960s (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Reorganization--Public Health Service, 1961-1968, undated (Box 3, Folder 23-24)
    - Report on a proposed OSG-Level "Standards" activity, 1968 January 22 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - "The Role of the Public Health Service in the Defense Community Facilities Program,", 1952 October 23 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Salk Vaccine, 1955 May 16 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Standard Setting, 1966-1968, undated (Box 4, Folder 28-29)
    - Water & Sewage Technical School, 1960-1964 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Water Pollution Control, 1954, 1963-1966, undated (Box 4, Folder 31-33)
- Additional Material, 1947-1981; Accession 1990-M-065; 1.0 linear foot (2 boxes)
  Addition inventory by Carol King, 1990 Jun
  Received from: M. Allen Pond, 1990 Jun
  - Health legislation background papers, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Moore, Jonathan, 1970-1975 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - National Advisory Health Council, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Noise control, background material for Congressional testimony, 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Reorganization of the Public Health Service (PHS), 1948, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Second session of the Ninetieth Congress
    - 1968 presidential campaign background papers--part I (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1968 presidential campaign background papers--part II (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - University of Pittsburgh, legislative delegation, 1973 May 2 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Water pollution control program, organizational locus, 1963-1965 (Box 2, Folder 9-10)
  - Miscellaneous papers pertaining to a variety of health policy issues, 1960s-1981 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous papers pertaining to aid to health professional schools, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - "Address Made Off The Record Before The American Society Of Newspaper Editors, By The Honorable Dean Acheson, Acting Secretary of State," Washington, 1947 April 18 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Additional Material, Accession 1999-M-046
  - General correspondence, 1968-1974
    - A (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - B (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - C (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - D (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "The Gestation and Birth of D/HEW: From Hayes to Eisenhower" [draft for article with background information], 1956, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 6)